"Are the Pollutant Levels in Fish
High Enough to Be Harmful?"
As I noted in my last video
on the subject,
if people choose to get their
long-chain omega-3s from fish,
the majority of consumers
would exceed the safety limits
for dioxins and dioxin-like
compounds (like PCBs).
But is there evidence
that exposure
to industrial pollutants
actually has
any adverse effects on us?
It does appear to be the case
that the general population
is exposed to sufficient
persistent organic pollutants,
both in terms of concentration
and diversity,
to induce metabolic disorders,
raising a potential
public health concern.
This assumption is based
on population studies,
which have found higher rates
of type 2 diabetes
among those with elevated
body burdens of chemicals,
along with interventional
studies in rodents
that established
a cause-and-effect relationship
between exposure
to these chemicals
and the development
of metabolic disorders,
including obesity
and insulin resistance.
If rats are fed a diet
high in farmed salmon fat,
for example, they gain
significantly more weight
compared to a diet
high in plant fat,
or a diet with largely
decontaminated salmon fat,
showing it was the contaminants
in the salmon to blame
for not just increasing
body fat,
but the worst kind of body fat:
deep abdominal visceral fat.
They also had an increase
in triglycerides
despite the omega-3s
and an increase in cholesterol,
along with a significant rise
in insulin levels,
because of a drop
in insulin sensitivity,
meaning they had
insulin resistance,
the cause of type 2 diabetes
and prediabetes.
The researchers concluded
that exposure to POPs,
these persistent
organic pollutants,
commonly present in foods
like farmed salmon
can lead to insulin resistance
and associated
metabolic disorders.
Okay, but what if you eat fish
so infrequently
you don’t exceed
the U.S. Environmental
Protection Agency’s
safety levels?
Like, only having
supermarket salmon
less than once every two weeks,
or less than once a month,
depending on where you buy it,
or less than once
every two months,
or once every four months?
The tolerable daily intakes
of these pollutants
are derived from things
like so-called
no-observed-adverse-effect
levels in animal studies,
where researchers
test the animal
most sensitive to these toxins
and give smaller
and smaller doses
until they find a dose
with no observable
adverse effects.
And then that dose
is taken and divided
by, like, a hundred
or a thousand
as a safety buffer
to arrive
at the tolerable human dose.
One of the limitations
with this approach
is that it tends only
to consider single chemicals,
one at a time.
What if a more
real-world experiment
were conducted where animals
were exposed
to a mixture of pollutants
but each at 500 times
lower than
the no-observed-adverse-effect
level,
at the quote-unquote
"tolerable" human intake?
Nothing should have happened,
right?
Each was 500 times smaller
than the dose
that causes any effects.
But when mixed together,
which is what actually happens
in fish and other seafood,
doses considered safe
for humans
are, in fact, not harmless
when exposure is chronic
and when pollutants
are administered in combination
in a context of what
too many Americans face.
Because seafood represents
one of the main sources
of human exposure to pollutants
that contribute
to metabolic diseases,
there is a call
on policymakers
to urgently regulate
and diminish the concentrations
of pollutants in fish
and other seafood
to protect
the general population.
Until that happens,
how can we stay away from them?
Well, we’re exposed
to flame retardant chemicals
in meat, including
fish and poultry;
PCBs in fish,
other meat, and dairy;
dioxins, the same thing:
fish, other meat, and dairy.
We’re exposed to PFOS
(forever chemicals) in seafood,
other meat, eggs,
dairy products,
and, in some places,
our drinking water.
If the highest
pollutant concentrations
are found in fish,
how are we going to get
our omega-3s?
The short-chain omega-3
found in walnuts and flaxseeds
may be sufficient,
since our body
can convert those
into the long-chain omega-3s
found in fish,
like EPA and DHA.
Pregnant
and breastfeeding women,
and those at greater risk
for poor conversion,
such as people with diabetes,
older adults,
and premature infants,
are especially most likely
to benefit
from algae-derived
DHA supplements,
which represent
a safe omega-3 source.